[Music]
这是平行折章节的第一部分
blue scissors and card and the details
需要的材料 胶水 剪刀和卡纸
of these are all explained in the
具体在教程1里解释过了
三种类型的平行折
introductory tutorial so there are three
这有三种平行折
kinds of parallel fault the first and
第一种 也差不多是最重要的
possibly the most important is the
平行四边形
parallelogram the parallelogram is a
平行四边形蛮有趣的
funny one when you open the base flat
当展开页面
the parallelogram goes flat it's only in
平行四边形也会摊平
dimension when the bases it's on is is
只在页面展开过程中是立体的
not flat the other two are the symmetric
另外两种分别是'对称平行折'
parallel fold so the length on each side
立起结构两侧
of the pop-up are exactly the same and
长度完全一致
the asymmetric parallel folds where the
'非对称平行折'
two lengths on the pop-up are different
立起结构两侧长度不同
so these last two we'll be doing in part
后两种在第二部分展开说
two parallel folds this this tutorial is
这节教程完全献给
completely devoted to the parallelogram
平行四边形
parallelograms can be used quite nicely
平行四边形在组合结构里很好用
in combination so here's an example you
这是个例子
can use them this way with the base as a
你可以像这样
base card as a base and a background in
把它们用作背景
which case this has created a whole
重叠多个图板
series of plates and you can stick
上面可以
bigger pieces of card onto any of those
粘一些别的元素
either vertical or horizontal so you can
不管是垂直还是水平方向
play with it that way
你可以这样横着玩
you can also play in it this way so yeah
也可以这样竖着玩
lots of potential there so first I just
有很多可能性
like to show some examples of the
我想先展示些例子
so this is Yankee and Cassidy's haunted house
先看下这本《鬼屋》
house on the first page we have this
第一页的楼梯
staircase this is actually two
这里有两个平行四边形
parallelograms this is the first one
右侧这是第一个
built into the gulley created by the
紧靠书中间谷沟
book this is the second one built into
左侧二楼这是另一个
the gulley created by the first
依附在前一个平行四边形的谷沟
parallelogram and when the page goes
页面完全展开时
flat the whole pop up goes flat the
立起结构也完全展开
second one this is a symmetric parallel
第二个 这是个对称平行折
fold so this fridge here the two sides
画面左右两侧是相同的
on each side they're both the same so
页面摊平时
when the page is flat the pop-up stands
立起结构弹起
up this is the third one this is one of
第三个
the other uses of the parallelogram is
这是平行四边形的另一种用法
it it creates that you can use it to to
用来制作动臂
make moving arms move and we'll be
这个在之后教程有详解
looking at that later in this tutorial
我们到时见
the next page well this is a this is a
下一页
curved shape that we look at in a much
这是个弧形结构
later tutorial but down here at the bath
也是之后教程内容 在这我们先注意
that is a that is a parallelogram you
底部澡盆这是个平行四边形
can look at it straight on as the page
可以直接看到
goes flat the bath goes flat so that's
页面展开时 它也摊平了
haunted house the other one I'd like to
这就是《鬼屋》几个例子
show you is sergeant charge
另一个要看的是《军士长》
this is sergeant charge illustrated by
作者是
Bill Bolton and if we look at this one
赵四
this is a parallelogram being used to
看下这一页   这是个平行四边形
turn over these figures so these are all
用来翻人物
slotted on but the basic strip that
画面元素都是用插槽串起来的
they're all attached to that is a
它们附着的基础纸带
parallelogram when the page is flat the
是平行四边形 页面展开时
parallelogram is flat but it gives a
是平行四边形摊平
really nice action to all those soldier
过程中给那些蚁人还是啥的玩意
ants or whatever they are so now I'll
产生很整齐的一个动作
show you how to make a parallelogram
现在我来演示 如何制作平行四边形
- 制作平行四边形
usually parallelograms are used values
通常 平行四边形就是酱紫
like this so we get a base sheet fold it
拿出卡纸做为基础页
in half fold it really funny take a
折一半 折彻底
piece of card to build with we'll use
再拿出张卡纸
pink so here's a pink piece just cut off
就骚粉色吧
a strip from one end doesn't matter how
从一端剪出个纸带
wide and then we need to actually make
宽度无所谓
it slightly shorter so maybe cut off an
需要稍微短点
inch or something and in this case
这里剪掉两三厘米
folder a gluing tab onto each end so
两端折出上胶水的粘口
gluing tabs should be roughly 1
粘口大概一厘米宽
centimeter wide or half an inch unless
如果有别的用途
you want them to be showing in which
你可以留出更大点粘口
case you can make them much bigger so
here it is and then you follow the
注意如果从
crease noting the middle that would be
纸带中间折叠
that would give you a symmetric parallel
得到的会是平行折
fold in this case because it's a
而我们想要的是平行四边形
parallelogram just make the make the
所以在
crease say a third of the way along or
三到四分之一地方折叠
1/4 of the way and of so you've got two
会得到两个不同长度
different lengths so this time put the
这时 把纸带折线
central crease on to your on to your
放在基础页中折线对齐
central put the crease on the pop-up on
to your central guarding of the base
mark where the where the crease lies
标记下折痕一边
either end it doesn't matter flip it
画个线即可长度不那么重要
round this is the important thing with
最重要的
these you flip it round so that the long
纸带翻个面
side is over the short piece on the base
这样 纸带长的一边会对到短的基础页
and the short side is over the long one
短的一边在基础页长的一边上方
and then you can because the
平行四边形
parallelogram lies flat when the whole
在基础页完全展开时是摊平的
whole base is flat you can actually glue
所以可以
both ends at the same time we just put a
同时给纸带两端上胶水
bit of glue on there
开始上胶水
and the tabs can actually point in or
粘口藏起来
out it that it really doesn't matter if
还是露外面无所谓的
you want them
如果要它们
it's where the crease lies that's
注意要把粘口折痕粘到标记线
important you have the tab in it's
粘口收起来挺重要的
hidden from view when you open it or you
它会从视觉上隐藏
can have it out as part of the design so
打开立起结构又会出现
there it is as the as the page closes
可以把这个特性作为设计的一部分
the parallelogram closes it's good good
像这样 合上基础页 平行四边形页页合上了
idea to really give it a good squash afterwards
afterwards just in case you're you're
measuring or gluing is a bit off so here
这样就行了
it is and you can use it this way or you
你可以这样竖着使用平行四边形
can use it this way or you can use it
可以平展开 也可以横着
this way so I'll just show you a couple
我下面展示些书中例子
of examples where books are made using
把平行四边形
parallelograms with the base as a base
用作基础结构或者背景
and the background so the first one I'd
第一个要展示的是
like to show you is cabassa
《穿靴子的猫》
puss-in-boots and the last spread is
最后页是个
this fantastic fairytale coach made
童话里的南瓜车
completely out of parallelograms if you
完全是用平行四边形做的
turn it turn it and look at it end on
从侧面看就能明显看出
you'll see it's all parallelograms as
书本合上时
you close it so the parallelograms
所有平行四边形也会折叠起来
closed down the other one I'd like to
另一本要看的是这个
show you is this one don't go out
《今晚别出门》
tonight by Babbitt Cole and in this one
这本书每一页都用类似的设计
every spread in this book is the same
the same type of design as you pull down
当拉下基础页
the base so the pop-up appears and if
立起结构就会显现
you look at these from end on or
如果从侧面看
sideways on you'll see that the whole
会发现所有机关都是
the whole thing is a series of
平行四边形的组合
parallelograms as you open and close it
开启或合上书本时
the parallelograms becomes 3d
平行四边形会有立体效果
okay no I'd like to show you how to
现在演示
build with parallelograms onto a v-fold
如何在V形折上添加平行四边形
so here's a v-fold made in one of the
这个是之前V形折课上做的
v-fold tutorials and we're going to
一个V形折
build a parallelogram
现在我们要在上面加平行四边形
there's gullies to build into there's a
平行四边形可以加在V形折侧的谷沟
gully here and on both sides whether
两侧都可以
we're the v-fold is attached to the page
V形折向页面合的时候
there's also a gunny in the middle in
V折背面也是个谷沟
the middle of the v-fold but again you
可以看到V折合起时
can see the gully closes as the v-fold
谷沟也会折叠
closes so we'll just take a couple of
我们从前面用了一半的卡纸
pieces of the fridge discards take a
剪下两片纸带
couple of slices off it so you take the
strip of cards start by making a fold on
纸带两端折叠
each end crease the fold thoroughly and
要折叠的彻底点
the these two files 1h and these are the
这两个纸带
two glowing tabs and the folds are both
各要折出两个粘口
parallel and then you make another fold
粘口都是平行的
roughly 1/3 of the way in it really
在大约1/3位置折一下
doesn't matter it depends what type of
不用担心 折多少不依赖
shape you wanting to create
你打算做的形状
but I'll go for roughly a third of the way along
我这里要做的是三分之一左右
way along so that's a third parallel
这是第三平行折
crease crease it really well and then
折仔细
I'll just trim off these corners it's
我要剪掉这些角
not not mechanically necessary but it
这不是必须步骤
think it stops them stops the jagged
只是觉得剪掉
bits snagging on things it seems to just
会少点锯齿
glue slightly better and so now you have
粘起来也更好看
a choice you can either put the parallel
现在可以做个选择
can parallelogram can either be built
可以粘这样
onto the pop-up like this and a long
长又矮的平行四边形
long and low parallelogram or it can be
或者是
built onto it like this so it's a tall
这样高点的
parallelogram by luck I've got it more
运气蛮好的
or less the same height as a as the
刚好折了个
v-fold
跟V折差不多高
so we're going to build a tall
所以就做个高点的平行四边形吧
parallelogram so we start by putting the
把平行四边形的折痕
the crease of the central crease of the
放在立起结构跟基础页的谷沟位置
parallelogram into the gully
mark weather where the crease lies it's
标记下折痕位置
always the crease that you measure to on
通常是测量的折痕是立起结构的
pop-ups so we mark where the crease lies
所以画条线标记
and then the crucial bit we flip it over
然后关键点 -- 翻转纸带
so you're going to glue the long sides
要把长的一边粘在
to the mark you've measured the short
刚标记位置
side and you actually glue the long side
测量的是短的一边 实际要粘的是长的一边
so we put glue on that tab smear it
给粘口上胶水
right to the right to the crease and
涂均匀
then glue the crease to the mark now you
粘到标记上
put the whole parallelogram into its
现在把平行四边形收起到
closed position
闭合状态
so the parallelograms in its closed
合上后
position but glue on the other tab and
给另一个粘口上胶水
then you can just close the base and it
然后可以合上基础页
finds its natural speaking position so
它会自动对位到自然的位置
there we go we've got parallelogram
就酱 展开页面
rising from the page though we've build
得到了平行四边形
another one into this this gully here so
然后我们给背面V折这里加平行四边形
I'll take another piece of card might as
用刚才另一个纸带
well just straighten this up slightly
捋直了
and maybe make it slightly shorter okay
发现或许应该短一点
we put a tab on each chain just like the
老动作 折粘口
other one another one somewhere not in
另一个粘口
the middle again maybe a third of the
三分之一处折叠
way
cut off the tabs as the quarters as
粘口跟平时一样 修下角
usual we get on of glue that into this
我们要把纸带粘到这个谷沟
this is going into this gully so put the
比划下先
done it again on just by luck I've just
哎呀呀 运气就是那么好
got it to the right length therefore any
尺寸刚刚好
longer and it wouldn't work so I put
再大一丢丢都放不下了
this crease into the central gully I
把一边的折痕跟中间谷沟对齐
mark where the fold lives so there's the
标记折痕在的位置
fold the crease line and now again the
再来做"关键动作"
crucial bit you flip it around so I've
翻转纸带
measured the short lengths flip it round
测量标记的是短的一边
I'm going to stick the long length on to
但是是把
that mark so I put glue on the glue on
长的一边粘到标记位置
that tab on the long side and glue it to
给长的一边粘口上胶水
the glue it to the mark there you go and
粘到标记上
this this could be high up on the v-fold
粘在V折高一点还是第一点
or low down on the v-fold doesn't matter
这你随意
and now you fold the whole piece into
把纸带折叠到闭合状态
its close position put glue on the other
上胶水
tab smear it to the crease
涂均匀
then you shut the hole
合上基础页
shut the whole base and the tab will
粘口会自动
find its natural sticking position
归位到合适的位置
okay I'd just like to explain the the
lengths involved in this so every pop-up
spans a gully so in this case this this
parallelogram is spanning this gully and
so every pop-up must be balanced on each
side of the gully so in this case it's
this length this length from the gully
on the base to where the long side
sticks down this length is the same as
this length and on the on the long side
this length the height between where the
top up the parallelogram is stuck to the
v-fold this height is the same as this
height and so that's what's giving you
that's what's giving you balance when
the whole thing is closed you see from
the gully on the v-fold you've got the
height of the v-fold plus a short bit of
the parallelogram and then you've got a
short bit of base and the longer to the
parallelogram and if you look at this
other one it's the same this this short
distance on the v-fold is the same as
this short distance on the parallelogram
and this long distance on the v-fold is
the same as the long distance on the
parallelogram so that's how you get
balanced with these parallelogram shapes
and I can actually show you this as well
on the on the earlier parallelogram
model I've just pointed out this this
short side on the parallelogram is the
same as this short side on the base and
the long side on the parallelogram is
the same as the long side on the base so
on the left-hand side you've got a short
length plus a long one on the right-hand
side you've got a long length plus a
short and so the two sides balance okay
I'll just show you the v-fold in
conjunction with the parallelogram this
book is jungle days by Helen bomber and
she's done a very imaginative use of the
v-fold here
this v-fold rather than it rising up
from the base this is coming forward
from the base so the surface of the
water is made with a v-fold in this case
all the other creatures the ducks the
kids the dog they're all based on
parallelograms lifted by the v-fold
so if we look at it end on here you can
see this there's parallelograms raised
raised by the v-fold raised by the
gulley here where the v-fold joins the
page and it's the same on the other side
you hear we got the dog and the and the
kids
these are parallelograms attached to the
v-fold so as the base closes as the
parrot as the v-fold goes down so the
parallelogram to close down the other
use of the parallelogram is for moving
arms so I'll just show you a quick way
of doing that in actual fact moving arms
is a highly complex aspect of pop up and
there will be a whole tutorial on moving
arms alone but it's an important use of
the parallelogram so I've just shown you
a quick basic way of doing it so here's
here's the base sheet and then we need a
piece to pop up from it so here's a
piece we just cut a chunk off the ends
we'll just make that slightly shorter
put tab on each ends these are parallel
folds with tab on each end and then trim
up the corners and in in this case
there'll be a third fold but this this
third fold keep it keep it quite near
the end so maybe you know one inch two
centimeters something like that
so make that third parallel fold fold it
really really well and now you take this
you fold it shut so this is this is font
closed and you just fold down the top
corner so you're folding this top edge
you close to close the parallelogram you
fold down this top edge to come down
against the the crease so you've got
that that little corner folded over and
this is actually a counter fold so you
can push that in and close it down so
there you are you've got the you've got
the counter fold now you put that this
is going to glue onto the bottom of your
page so put the line up this this middle
crease of the of the pop-up piece mark
where they crease it the the short end
lies on the page so you you just mark
where that crease nice now crucial with
parallelograms you flip it over so
you're not going to stick though you're
gonna stick the long ends to that mark
make sure that make sure this double
triangle is up because it's a
parallelogram it goes flat when the base
is flat so you can put glue on both ends
at the same time smear the glue up to
the crease
and you can glue that glue that down so
you you measure the short distance but
you're gluing the long side too to the
mark and you can glue the other end at
the same time with the whole piece flat
so here it is the whole piece is flat as
you as you close the page just make sure
it all all works nicely and now you you
can push that that counter fold in and
fold it shut right now you can attack
I've made this ever so slightly rough
actually now you can take a piece to use
as a moving of the cut this slightly
slightly narrower this is going to stick
on to the small the triangle on the
small side so we just cut that corner
off and stick this on to that on to that
triangle so this sticks down there and
as the as the base closes I'm not sure
yeah that's fine
as the base closes the the arm moves
down and you can actually enhance the
visual effect if you if you put a elbow
in the arm so if we stick an extra piece
on there you'll get an impression of
even more movement so glue that on there
and now you've dropped the you've got
the moving on and there's a very good
example in the haunted house that I
showed you
oh yeah here's the haunted house and it
was on the third page here is it's the
parallelogram opening and
guerilla moves and it's actually really
interesting if you look at these moving
arms you've got the the triangle that's
on the short side of the parallelogram
and you've got the triangle on the long
side this arm attached to the short side
as the page closes it rotates against
the page this arm attached to the long
side of the parallelogram as the page
closes it flips over so this is this is
quite important about moving arms moving
arms a very sophisticated mechanism
动臂机制比较复杂
there's a lot more to it you need to
如果想了解更多
watch the moving arm tutorial which
请关注后面动臂的专门教程
comes later it's all in my book pop-up
也可以
design from paper mechanics and it
可以考虑下我的书「pop-up design and paper mechanics」
explains parallelograms and moving arms
里面有平行四边形详解
in great detail
和动臂的详细章节
[字幕：Cash Yang][公众号：2274]
[关注公众号获取更多分享]
[公众号：2274]